Guide to the Walter Tuchscherer Papers 1905-1978
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Walter Tuchscherer Papers
1905-1978
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 343
Tuchscherer, Walter, d. 1960
0.5 linear feet, 12 artifacts, 88 photographs
Walter Tuchscherer was a brewer and pharmacist in Montana and other western states. This collection contains items that pertain to Walter Tuchscherer's life, with documents dating from 1905-1978.
Biographical Note
Walter Tuchscherer graduated from Gonzaga in University, Spokane, Washington in 1909. Due to his interest in the family brewery business, he graduated from the Hantke's Brewer's School in Milwaukee in 1915. Walter was fluent in German, and was deployed to the Siberian front in 1918 to serve as a translator for the United States intelligence division. Returning to Anaconda, Montana, in 1919, Walter found the family brewery closed due to Prohibition. Walter became a co-owner of Washoe Coal, with his brother-in-law, R. A. Kelly, and married Maybelle Malloy on June 9, 1921.
In 1925, the Tuchscherer family became the owners of the Standard Drug store. Walter again returned to school, this time to the Capitol School of Pharmacy in Denver, Colorado. Walter passed the state boards in 1930 to become a pharmacist. When Prohibition ended, Walter returned to working at the Anaconda Brewery. Walter worked at the brewery during the days, which left his wife, Maybelle, to run the drug store in the day, and at night Walter attended to his pharmacist career. The Anaconda Brewery closed in 1958, where Walter returned to working at the pharmacy full-time. Walter died in 1960.
This collection contains items that pertain to Walter Tuchscherer's life, with documents dating from 1905-1978. The collection contains memorabilia from Walter's college years at Gonzaga College, World War I memorabilia from Siberia, and writings by Walter and correspondence to and from Walter. There are clippings from World War I, clippings about his wedding, his involvement with the B.P.O.E., the Knights of Columbus, the Boy Scouts, and the Rotary Club. This collection also contains artifacts and photographs. The artifacts are personal items of Walter's from college, World War I, and the Boy Scouts. The photographs include pictures from World War I - personal photos and souvenir photos, and a photograph of the graduating class from the 1915 Hantke's Brewer's School in Milwaukee.
The collection is divided into seven series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1 folder, 1909-1930
Series II: Writings, 1 folder, 1910
Series III: World War I, 6 folders, 1917-1919
Series IV: Clippings, 7 folders, 1913, 1921-1922, and 1978
Series V: Memorabilia, 1 folder and 1 oversize item, 1905, 1907-1909
Series VI: Artifacts, 12 artifacts, 1908-1909, 1917-1921
Series VII: Photographs, 88 photographs, 1915-1921
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Materials in this collection were retained by the Tuchscherer Family until donation the K. Ross Toole Archives.
Gift of Dr. Mabel D. Tuchscherer, 1992.
Materials in this collection were formerly part of Mss 167, the Anaconda Brewery Papers. During reprocessing of Mss 167 Walter Tuchscherer's materials were identified as a separate collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Personal papers--Montana--Anaconda; Photographs; Artifacts
Boy Scouts--Montana--Anaconda; Breweries--Montana--Anaconda; Drugstores--Montana--Anaconda; Friendly societies--Montana--Anaconda; German Americans--Montana--Anaconda; Men--Montana--Anaconda--Societies and clubs; Pharmacists--Montana--Anaconda; Veterans--Montana--Anaconda; World War, 1914-1918--Military intelligence--United States; World War, 1914-1918--Veterans--Montana--Anaconda; World War, 1914-1918--Russia (Federation)--Siberia
Anaconda (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Elks (Fraternal order); Gonzaga University--Alumni and alumnae; Hantke's Brewers' School (Milwaukee, Wis.)--Alumni and alumnae; Knights of Columbus; Rotary International
Montana; Artifacts; Photographs; Labor History; German Americans
- Correspondence, 1909-1930; Series I; 1 folder
  There are three letters in this series. There is a letter from Walter to his parents while at Gonzaga College, a letter from his mother while he was at war, and a letter to Walter from Father Patrick J. O'Rielly.
  - Correspondence, 1909-1930 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Writings, 1910; Series II; 1 folder
  This series has three writings by Walter. One is a paper titled A Defense of the South and Something about Robert E. Lee that is dated March 2, 1910. The other two writings are in speech form: one titled College Ideals and the other is about the culture of brewing and breweries; both are undated.
  - Writings, 1910 and undated (Box-folder 1/2)
- World War I, 1917-1919; Series III; 6 folders
  This series contains memorabilia from Walter's service in World War I. Items include pamphlets distributed to the soldiers, personal notes in notebooks about war tactics, clippings about World War I, and postcards.
  - Walter H. Tuchscherer, 27th Infantry, ca. 1917-1919 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Memorabilia - pamphlets and brochures, ca. 1917-1919 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Memorabilia - blank stationery, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Clippings (photocopies), 1918 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Walter H. Tuchscherer's Notebooks, ca. 1918 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Postcards, ca. 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Clippings, 1913, 1921-1922, and 1978; Series IV; 7 folders
  The clippings in this series contain clippings about the wedding of the Tuchscherer's, and about Walter's involvement in the B.P.O.E., Knights of Columbus, the Anaconda Boy Scouts, and the Rotary Club. There is also an excerpt from A History of Montana pertaining to Henry Mueller, Walter's uncle, who was a former Mayor of Butte, and owner of five breweries, including the Anaconda Brewery and Centennial Brewery in Butte.
  - Wedding, June 1921 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - B.P.O.E., 1922 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Knights of Columbus, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Boy Scouts of Anaconda, 1922 and Boy Scouts of Deer Lodge Constitution, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Rotary Club, 1922 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Henry Mueller, 1913; A History of Montana by Helen Fitzgerald Sanders, Vol. III, The Lewis Publishing Co., Chicago and New York, pp. 1303-1304 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - City Drug, 1978 (Box-folder 1/15)
- Memorabilia, 1905, 1907-1909; Series V; 1 folder and 1 oversized item
  This series includes a program of Anaconda High School's 1907 commencement ceremony and Walter's diploma. There are also Gonzaga College programs and catalogs. The Gonzaga catalog's and programs are from oratorical contests and a catalog of officers and students from the year 1908-1909.
  - Anaconda High School and Gonzaga College materials, 1905, 1907-1909 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Anaconda High School diploma, 1907 (Box-folder OS4)
- Artifacts, 1908-1909, 1917-1921; Series VI; 12 artifacts
  This series includes personal items of Walter Tuchscherer that he collected while at Gonzaga College and serving in the Army during World War I. Items include his junior and senior class pins, his 1909 oratorial pin, and a boy scout arm band. His military artifacts include a sewing kit, swagger stick, Russian coin bracelet, souvenir box, a coconut from Hawaii, two cloth bags, and a two-liter stein.
  - Gonzaga College Junior Class Pin, 1908; 1 (Box 2)
  - Gonzaga College Senior Class Pin, 1909; 2 (Box 2)
  - Gonzaga College Oratorial Pin, 1909; 3 (Box 2)
  - Boy Scout Arm Band, undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - Swagger stick, probably from Army experience in Siberia during World War I, ca. 1917-1919; 5 (Box 2)
  - Sewing kit, probably from Army experience in Siberia during World War I, ca. 1917-1919; 6 (Box 2)
  - Russian coin bracelet (1915-1916) given by Walter Tuchscherer to Margaret Kelly Kenny, 1921; 7 (Box 2)
  - Souvenir Box, "Valdivostok, 1919", 8 (Box 2)
  - Souvenir Coconut carving from Hawaii, undated; 9 (Box 2)
  - Cloth bag with a key inside, undated; 10 (Box 2)
  - Blue cloth bag, undated; 11 (Box 2)
  - Two-liter beer stein made in West Germany and is inscribed with, "W.H. Tuchscherer", undated; 12 (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1915-1921; Series VII; 88 photographs
  A majority of the photographs from this series are photos from Walter's World War I service. Other photographs include those from his wedding and his 1915 graduating class from the Hantke's Brewer's School in Milwaukee.
  - Line of men on horses, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)1 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Train car with people inside, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)2 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Train car with people inside, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)3 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Military men, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)4 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - A building with people in front, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)5 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Structure, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)6 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Man and a horse in snow, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)7 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Man and a horse in snow, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)8 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Man standing on a horse, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)9 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Man holding a horse, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)10 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Man and a dog, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)11 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Camp Kharashaw tents, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)12 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Men standing in a street, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)13 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Landscape, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)14 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Girls standing in a line, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)15 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Men in a field, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)16 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Two horses and a wagon forging a river, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)17 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Horse and a wagon going down a street, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)18 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Tents, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)19 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Men, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)20 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Military men, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)21 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Men working, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)22 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Horse and wagon, two crossing a river, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)23 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Men and tents, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)24 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Men and tents, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)25 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Men sitting by a railroad, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)26 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Line of people, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)27 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Landscape, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)28 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Men pulling a wagon, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)29 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Landscape, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)30 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Unidentified, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)31 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Open air market, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)32 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Group of military men, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)33 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Landscape, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)34 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Wagons, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)35 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Men at the side of a train, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)36 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Men at the side of a train, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)37 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Man on a horse, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)38 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Man standing in snow, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)39 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - People tending a field, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)40 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - People, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)41 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Woman, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)42 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - People on a horse, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)43 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Man, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)44 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Man, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)45 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Men in snow, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)46 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Landscape, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)47 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Landscape, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)48 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Children on steps of St. Louish Church, France, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)49 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Woman and a dog, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)50 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Man in a suit, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)51 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - "Liberty Theater", circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)52 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - "Liberty Theater", circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)53 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Man and a black bear, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)54 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Maybelle and Walter Tuchscherer's wedding picture with wedding party, (including Margaret Kelly and Louis Andrews and more), June 9, 1921; 343(VII)55 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Train wreck, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)56 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Military men, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)57 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Two military men in Liberia, August 1919, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)58 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Railroad tunnel #39 of Travbailkal Railway, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)59 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Railroad, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)60 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Ruins at St. Baikal, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)61 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - "Alexander destroyed by the Bolshiveks, Lake Baikal", circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)62 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - St. Baikal, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)63 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Bridge across River Irkut, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)64 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Bridge across River Kitoe, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)65 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Station Baikal, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)66 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Prayer at Irkustsk Railway Station in remembrance of Col. Uschalkoff, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)67 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Bridge across River Beloi, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)68 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Funeral for Col. Uschalkoff, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)69 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Theatrical troupe 27th Infantry, with Walter Tuchscherer in photo, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)70 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Ship sunk by Bolshiviks, River Angara, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)71 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Ship in snow, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)72 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Station Baikal after an explosion, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)73 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Bridge across River Orzone, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)74 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Captain Kalletz, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)75 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Ataman Cmenoff, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)76 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Czecko Slovak staff, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)77 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Colonel Pepejaef, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)78 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Admiral A.V. Kolchak, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)79 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Group of military men, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)80 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - General Gaida, circa 1918-1919; 343(VII)81 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Postcard of Anaconda Standard's front page, November 11, 1919; 343(VII)82 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Postcard of Palace Hotel and Market Street, San Francisco, California, undated; 343(VII)83 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Postcard of Greek Catholic Church of Siberia, undated; 343(VII)84 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Postcard of Verkhne-Udinsk, Siberia, undated; 343(VII)85 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Postcard of the interior of a church, undated; 343(VII)86 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Graduating class of the Hantke's Brewer's School in Milwaukee, 1915; 343(VII)87 (Box-folder OS4)
  - Walter Tuchcherer at Hantke's Brewer's School, ca. 1915; 343(VII)88 (Box-folder 3/21)